Guide to the Douglas Wayne Male Papers ALBA.223
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Douglas Wayne Male Papers
1937-1939
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Male, Douglas Wayne.
ALBA.223
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Douglas Wayne Male volunteered in the Spanish Civil War and served in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. He died at Gandesa in April 1938. The collection contains letters he wrote to his sister and brother-in-law, Lee and Sam Kutnick detailing his experiences in Spain. The collection also includes correspondence by another volunteer, Boleslaw Sliwon, Spanish military documents attesting to the disappearance of Douglas Male and Jack Taub at Gandesa, and two sheets of colored stamps (imprinted S.R.I.) sold in aid of war victims in Spain.
Provenance
The Douglas Wayne Male papers were donated to New York University by ALBA, via Peter Carroll, in 2004.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Douglas Wayne Male was born in Kentucky and was living in San Francisco in 1937 when he left for Spain to volunteer in the Spanish Civil War. He was then 23 years old. He sailed to Europe on the Berengaria on July 3, 1937, arriving in Spain on July 24th. Lists in the International Brigade Archives describe him as a seaman, single and a member of the Young Communist League from 1936. He died at Gandesa in April 1938.
He corresponded regularly with his sister and brother-in-law, Lee and Sam Kutnick, and signed most of his letters from Spain with the nickname "DUD."
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Correspondence, 1937-1938, consists of letters written by Male mostly to his sister and brother-in-law, Lee and Sam Kutnick, detailing his experience in Spain. Letters from another seaman volunteer, Boleslaw Sliwon to Lee Kutnick are also in this collection. Postcards from Male and from Sliwon to various people (including Harry Bridges) and a postcard from a Spanish Communist are also included. Letters from Jack Taub and Elhanon Bridges and miscellaneous letters from others, including a volunteer who signs himself "Bob," complete the correspondence.
Series II: Subject Files, 1937-1939, consists of a portrait postcard and ticket autographed by Dolores Ibarruri; two Spanish military documents attesting to the disappearance of Douglas Male and Jack Taub at Gandesa; a clipping from Frente Rojo, 1937; and two sheets of colored stamps (imprinted S.R.I.) sold in aid of war victims in Spain.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Correspondence.
II, Subject Files.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Photographs and 34 blank postcards from Spain were transferred to the ALBA photograph and postcard collections.
Personal papers.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Correspondence.; Barcelona (Spain); Articles.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Madrid (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Bay Area Post; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Sliwon, Boleslaw.; Taub, Jack.; Male, Douglas Wayne.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1937-1938.
  - Bridges, Elhanon W. to Sam Kutnick, Jun 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Male, Douglas Wade, to Mario Caseroli, Nov 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - Male, Douglas Wade, to Ethel Horowitz, Mar 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Male, Douglas Wade, to Lee Kutnick (sister), Jul 1937-Jul 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Male, Douglas Wade, to Sam Kutnick (brother-in-law), Nov 1937-Feb 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sliwon, Boleslaw to Sam Kutnick, Nov 1937-Jul 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Taub, Jack to Lee and Sam Kutnick, Feb 1938-Mar 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, undated, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Postcards (from DWM and Boleslaw Sliwon), undated, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1937-1939.
  - Clippings, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ibarruri, Dolores: Autograph and Postcards, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitation to dinner for Alvarez del Vayo from Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, May 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Stamps, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)